<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Pretious apple proceeding from the tree of life, or, A Sweet and seasonable word, dropping from the lips of the righteous. Being an effectuall meanes to preserve the lives of men, sincerely applying it from generation, to generation. : Presented to the view of that terrible army, who under God have been a defence unto us, from the monsterous, wild, ravenning and venemous beasts of the howling wildernes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3209B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504506</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2593:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Pretious apple proceeding from the tree of life, or, A Sweet and seasonable word, dropping from the lips of the righteous. Being an effectuall meanes to preserve the lives of men, sincerely applying it from generation, to generation. : Presented to the view of that terrible army, who under God have been a defence unto us, from the monsterous, wild, ravenning and venemous beasts of the howling wildernes.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
            <head>A PRETIOUS APPLE PROCEEDING from the Tree of Life, OR <hi>A ſweet and ſeaſonable word, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from the lips of the Righteous.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Being an effectuall meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the lives of men, ſincerely applying it <hi>from generation, to generation.</hi> Preſented to the view of that terrible Army, who under God have been a defence unto us from the monſterous, wild, ravenning and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Beaſts of the howling Wildernes.</head>
            <p>AS the Saints on earth have both Spirits ſoules and bodies, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. ſo they are to uſe (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of other Saints) not onely ſpirituall weapons againſt their enemies, who mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them after a ſpirituall manner, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. but alſo outward meanes (as well offenſive as defenſive) againſt thoſe who do outwardly aſſault them; yet alwayes with
<pb facs="tcp:171821:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
this caveat, that as they are to uſe the world, as though they uſed it not, ſo thoſe things where with they defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and offend their enemies, ought to be uſed by the Saints for meer neceſſity; and with all, we are to mind that they are the weapons of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> whoſe own ſword ſhall cut off his own head, as <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword did his.</p>
            <p>And as the Kingdome of God conſiſteth not in meate and drink, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. no more doth it in outward warfare, or defence of themſelves, from the hands of thoſe who do out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly aſſault them (according to their uſuall manner) yet as the Saints of God have need of meate and drinke for the nouriſhment of their bodies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.42, 43, 45. that ſo their outward man periſh not for want of foode, leaſt they be diſabled to ſerve God.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſt preferrs the life and body before food, and rayment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25. ſo they have need of outward helpes to defend their bodies and lives, in caſe they be in imminent danger to be moleſted and aſſaulted by their enemies, and the Saints of God are bound to take one anothers part, in ſuch acaſe, <hi>Eſt.</hi> 9.1.2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 18.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Moſes,</hi> though he had not received his outward calling (which he had at the Buſh) to go immediately and deliver <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet did he after a wiſe and warie manner reſcue an <hi>Iſralite</hi> out of the hands of an Egiptian; <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 11.12. So <hi>Deborah</hi> did accompany <hi>Barack</hi> to deſtroy the enemies of God, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.10. which kept them in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, <hi>verſe</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Inhabitants of <hi>Meroz</hi> did not come to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty enemies (though with worldly weapons) they were accurſed with a bitter curſe, and that by the Angel of the Lord, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Iael</hi> for wounding of <hi>Siſſera</hi> (though it was with a workmans hammer, and a nayle of the Tent) ſhe was not condemned, but commended and bleſſed above other
<pb facs="tcp:171821:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
women, <hi>ver.</hi> 24, 25, 26, 27. And <hi>Sampſon</hi> when God gi him bodily ſtrength, defended himſelfe therewith againſt the <hi>Philiſtims, Cap.</hi> 15.15. and that unto the day of his death, <hi>Cap.</hi> 16.30.</p>
            <p>So the workmen of <hi>Nehemia,</hi> who builded the walles of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> had their ſwords, ſpeares, and bowes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend themſelves, and offend their enemies, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.13. in caſe they ſhould aſſault them; and the one part of the people were ſet to defend the other part, and the buildiers of the wall had ſwords girded by their ſides and ſo builded, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>By theſe clear Texts of Scrip<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, with the example of divers other holy Saints of God, it is evident that all the Saints on earth have ſufficient ground and warrant to uſe all outward helpes they can, to preſerve their bodies, as well as inward for the preſervation of their ſoules; For as God hath ordained ſpirituall meanes for the prefervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule, ſo hath he afforded outward helpes for the defence and preſervation of the body; And Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him that had no ſword, to ſell his garment and buy one, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.36.</p>
            <p>And the Holy Ghoſt in the <hi>Revelation</hi> doth expreſſe the puniſhment, which ſhould be inflicted upon the wicked, and not onely deſcribeth the perſons who are to execute the ſame, but alſo preſcribeth both the manner &amp; the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thereof, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.7. The executioners are the Saints; the manner of puniſhment is to reward her as ſhe hath rewarded them, and the meaſure is, that they ſhall double it, and in the ſame cup which ſhe hath filled, they ſhall fill unto her the double.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt be puniſhed twofold, Spiritually and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally; Spiritually, by the ſword of the Spirit which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth out of the mouth of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. Corporally,
<pb facs="tcp:171821:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
puniſhments inflicted upon their bodies; even as <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> hath not only murdered ſoules (by leading them into the way of deſtruction) <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.13. but bodies alſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. yea and the bodies of the Saints, they have killed many wayes, as Satan and his inſtruments deviſed; <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath done unto others, ſo ſhall it be done unto him.</p>
            <p>And as his Kingdome was built and hath been upholden by blood, ſo ſhall it be ruinated and deſtroyed by blood; <hi>for he that ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, Chap.</hi> 16.5.6. and becauſe the members of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> have ſhed the blood of the Saints and Prophets, God hath given and will give them blood to drink, becauſe they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it, and they ſhall have it duly and truly paid them after the ſame manner, though it be alſo in a double mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and the Saints in doing this, do a worke of mercy, and thoſe who hinder it, do a worke of cruelty, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.11.12. for mercy to the bad, is cruelty to the good.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
